Latin American mss.--Argentina, 1612-1944 LMC 1605
Lilly Library
Latin American mss.--Argentina
1612-1944
2012
Lilly Library
LMC 1605
3 Boxes 3 standard
4 bound
2 folios oversize
The Latin American mss. Argentina, 1612-1944, consist of material principally about the independence period of Argentina for the years 1806-1823.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Historical Note
Argentina declared independence from Spain in 1816, which served as a defining event in the revolutionary war involving Spain and the Liberating Army of the Andes that lasted until a cessation of hostilities was signed in 1823. The Liberating Army of the Andes and other Argentinian revolutionaries played a large role in the independence movements of other South American nations as well.
Scope and Content Note
The Latin American mss. Argentina, 1612-1944, contain material principally about the independence period of Argentina for the years 1806-1823. Included are documents about the English invasions of Buenos Aires in 1806-1807: the capitulation of Buenos Aires on July 2, 1806, the treaty of July 7, 1807, between the British and the Spanish, correspondence between the cabildos of Buenos Aires, Cuzco, and Huamanga, and the journal of Thomas Murray, a participant in the invasions. Coverage of the military aspects of the war of independence from the revolutionary and royalist sides is reflected in the military reports of the Spanish generals Jose Manuel de Goyeneche y Barreda and Pio Tristan, account sheets of the Liberating Army of the Andes, a set of twenty-four muster rolls for November 8-15, 1819, and information about the preparations for the campaign in Peru by the Liberating Army of the Andes, particularly a series of thirty-one letters from Jose de San Martin to Jose Pescara dealing with supplies for the army during the years 1814-1816. Other documents of interest concern the mutiny in San Juan by Mariano Mendizabel and other officers of the Liberating Army of the Andes against their commander, Rudecindo Alvarado, in 1820, a report about the political situation in San Juan on February 12, 1820, and letters written by Alvarado to San Martin about the mutiny; the defeat and death of Jose Miguel Carrera; the peace convention between the provinces of Buenos Aires, Santa Fe, and Entre Rios on February 23, 1820; and the cessation of hostilities between Buenos Aires and Spain in 1823.
Materials for the colonial period are transfers of land titles, promissory notes, inventories of estates, a will, and an antenuptial contract.
Documents for the national period of Argentine history include some items concerning the dictatorship of Juan Manuel Jose Domingo Ortiz de Rosas, a brief resume of the murder trial of Paulino Rojas, letters and articles of Domingo Faustino Sarmiento, and letters of Guillermo Furlong Cardiff and Teodoro Becu discussing the history of printing in Argentina.
The collection has four bound volumes. Historia argentina del descubrimiento, poblacion y conquista de las Provincias del Rio de la Plata, written by Rui Diaz de Guzman in 1612, was published in the first volume of Pedro de Angelis' Coleccion de obras y documentos relativos a la historia antigua y moderna de las provincias del Rio de la Plata, Buenos Aires, Imprenta Editora de V. Colmegna, 1900 (F2801 .A48 v. 1). Sebastian de Undiano y Gastelu's Ytinerario de Mendoza a Buenos aires por el camino de las Postas escritas en Mendoza en 1799 has been published in the Anuario de historia argentina, ano 1940, v. 2, 531-542 (F2801 .A53). Coleccyon de varios papeles apologeticos en prosa y verso is a 1786 work with the name of Melchor Lopez y Cossio appended.
Note on Indexing Terms - "Law": There is a large quantity of legal material pertaining to Latin America in these collections. Royal and viceregal decrees, both de oficio and de parte, are especially numerous.
Note on Indexing Term - "Religion": A large quantity of this material relates to religious matters.
Note on Indexing Term - "West (U.S.)" and "Americana": There are items pertaining to early settlements and colonial government in Texas, California and New Mexico, and information on Texas independence.
Acquisition Information
Gift: 2012
Related Materials
There are other collections of Latin materials, grouped by country, also located at the Lilly Library, Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana:
Bolivia
Brazil
British Guiana
British Honduras
Chile
Chile
Costa Rica
Costa Rica
Dominican Republic
Dominican Republic
Guatemala
Guatemala Music
Honduras
Honduras
Mexico II
Mexico III
Nicaragua
Panama
Paraguay
Peru
Peru II
Puerto Rico
Salvador
Uruguay
Venezuela
International relations; Law; Religion; Americana; West (U.S.); Argentina--History; Argentina --History --1810-; Argentina--Politics and government
- Manuscript Material
  - 1627-1686 (Box 1)
  - Registro principal., 1737, Oct. 31-1757, July 28 (Box 1)
  - 1716-1757 (Box 1)
  - Ramos, Francisco. Marriage contract..., 1743, Oct. 2 (Box 1)
  - Arrascaeta, Gregorio de. Inventory of tobacco., 1774, May 5 (Box 1)
  - 1767-1774 (Box 1)
  - Expediente concerning the case of Manuel Ferreyra de la Cruz against María Antonia Días., 1774, Aug. 16-1781, June 6 (Box 1)
  - Uriarte. Documents concerning Bernardo Pastor, 1781, May 7-1784, June 25 (Box 1)
  - Murray, Thomas. Journal of Sargeant Thos. Murray's Travels During the Late Wars., 1790, Jan. 2-1814, June 3 (Box 1)
  - 1782-1786 (Box 1)
  - 1789-1799 (Box 1)
  - 18th cent. (Box 1)
  - 1800-1805 (Box 1)
  - 1806 (Box 1)
  - 1807 (Box 1)
  - 1808 (Box 1)
  - 1809 (Box 1)
  - 1810-1811 (Box 2)
  - 1812, Jan.-Sept. (Box 2)
  - 1812, Oct.-Dec. (Box 2)
  - 1813-1814 (Box 2)
  - San Martín, José de. To Pescara, José., 1814, Oct. 24-1816, Oct. 27 (Box 2)
  - 1815 (Box 2)
  - 1816 (Box 2)
  - 1817-1818 (Box 2)
  - 1819, Jan.-Apr. (Box 2)
  - Guido, Rufino. Reports concerning the funds needed to pay the troops., 1819, May 30-July 31 (Box 2)
  - 1819 (Box 2)
  - 1819, June-Dec. (Box 2)
  - Lemos, Juan Gregorio. To Alvarado, Rudecindo., 1819, June 28-Aug. 12 (Box 2)
  - Necochea, Eugenio. Muster rolls., 1819, Nov. 8-15 (Box 2)
  - Ejército de los Andes. QUaderno de Altas y Baxas..., 1820, Jan.-Mar. (Box 2)
  - 1820, Jan. 10-Jan. 20 (Box 2)
  - (incomplete). Alvarado, Rudecindo. To San Martín, José de., 1820, Jan. 20-Feb. 28; Feb. (Box 2)
  - 1820, Jan 31-Feb. 20 (Box 2)
  - Sarratea, Manuel de, et al. Peace treaty between provinces of Buenos Aires, Santa Fé, and Entre Ríos., 1820, Feb. 23 (Box 2)
  - 1820, Sept. 3-Nov. 28 (Box 2)
  - Godoy Cruz, Tomás. To O'Higgins, Bernardo., 1820, Oct. 14-Nov. 11 (Box 2)
  - 1821 (Box 2)
  - 1822 (Box 2)
  - 1823 (Box 2)
  - 1824 (Box 2)
  - 1825-1829 (Box 2)
  - 1831-1834 (Box 2)
  - n.d. Miscellaneous. (Box 2)
  - Rojas, Paulino. To Alsina, Valentin., 1832, Apr. 12 (Box 2)
  - 1835-1840 (Box 2)
  - 1841-1845 (Box 2)
  - 1846-1852 (Box 2)
  - 1853-1859 (Box 2)
  - 1860-1870 (Box 2)
  - 1870-1900 (Box 2)
  - n.d., 1900- (Box 2)
  - Undiano, John Lawrence. The Life of Sebastian de Undiano y Gastelú, 1758-1829, 2011 (Box 3)
- Individually Bound Materials
  - Piaz de Guzman, Rui. Historia Argentina..., 1612 (Bound)
  - Coleccyon de varios..., 1786 (Bound)
  - Zavaleta, Diego Estanislao, 1760-1843. Elementa Philosophie universe..., 1795; Autograph document signed 347 p. + 9 p. 21 cm. Vellum binding; Index; On page 347 pen and ink drawing of a bird with foliage in mouth; Two pen and ink drawings illustrating principles of physics mounted on inside lower cover. (Bound)
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Source of purchase by Lathrop C. Harper, 8 West 40th Street, New York, New York, 10018, unknown. Harper lot 24956. 1968.
    Related Materials
    See Zavaleta's doctoral dissertation, Theses canonicae (Buenos-Ayres: Real Imprenta de los Niños Expósitos, 1789); BX1935 .R696; also at the Lilly Library, Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana.
    Biographical / Historical
    This manuscript appears to be a previously unrecorded copy of the second part of Zavaleta's Elementa universae philosophiae, a work which exists only in manuscript. The other parts and another copy of part 2 "Physical generalis" are all held in Buenos Aires. The second copy of part 2 (4o, 196 pages) is in the Biblioteca Nacional; part 3 (the "Physica particularis"; 4o, 175 pages) in the library of the Consejo Nacional de Educación; and part 4 (the "Metaphysica"; 4o, 456 unnumbered pages) in the Convent of Santo Domingo. No copy of a part 1 is attested.
    Each of the other manuscripts, save the second copy of the "Physica generalis," claims to be by someone who personally heard ("me audiente") the Elementa propounded by Zavaleta himself: part 2 by Tomás García de Zúñiga; part 3 by Juan Manuel Fernández de Agüero; and part 4 by Juan José Castañer [see: Bibliography of the philosophy in the Iberian colonies of America / Redmond, Walter Bernard (The Hague: Martinus Nijhoff, 1972) entries 820-822, pages 109-110.]
    Just as Part 2 bears the date August 3rd, 1795, part 3 is dated July 10th, 1796. Part 4 is undated.
    Copies of both title-pages and the drawing from the copy of part 2 (which matches that at the back of the Lilly's copy, albeit not exactly) may be found in El Deán de Buenos Aires Diego Estanislao de Zavaleta / Guiñazú, Enrique Ruiz (Buenos Aires: Ediciones Peuser, 1952). All copies seem to be in different hands. The part of the "Generalis physica" reproduced in Guiñazú which overlaps that of the Lilly copy reveals that the copies are not identical.
    There is a detailed overview of each of the works in: Nacimento y desarrollo de la filosofia en el Rio de la Plata 1536-1810 / Fulong, Guillermo (Buenos Aires: Guillermo Kraft, 1952) pages 364-370, who considers Zavaleta one of the three greatest Scholastics of late 18th century Argentina, along with Mariano Medrano and José Valentín Gómez. Guiñazú's summary of the work highlights what's probably most striking about it: "El texto de las lecciones de física que dictó el doctor Zavaleta en 1795, demuestra un verdadero esfuerzo de aplicación para difundir el conocimiento de las leyes de la naturaleza, siendo de admirar cómo tal enseñanza podÍa hacerse valedera sin el empleo del cálculo, sin la experimentación y con pocos instrumentos de gabinete. Sólo la autorizada palabra del maestro, su exposición intuitiva, de principios y aforismos, era el bagage depositado en la mente del alumnado ... pues afirma Gutiérrez que 'tenemos motivos para creer que el curso del Dr. Zavaleta fué redactado con mayor esmero y mayor copia de luces entre cuantos se dieron en el Colegio carolino, especialmente en la materia de que tratamos'" [Guiñazú, page 22; see also: Origen y desarrollo de la enseñanza pública superior en Buenos Aires (2nd ed.) / Gutierrez, Juan María (Buenos Aires: La Cultura Argentina, 1915), page 317].
    Scope and Contents
    Translated title
    Elements | of universal Philosophy | In kindness to | the studious youth of the | Real Colegio de San Carlos, Buenos Aires | for the scholarly use of the boarding school | adapted by D. D. Diego Estanislao | Zavaleta former | alumnus of the boarding school | and now professor of | Philosophy in | the same. | As I heard it, Tomás | García de Zúñiga
    Part 2. | or | the General Physics. | begun the 3rd | of August | in the year of the | Lord 1795.
    Translated table of contents
    Index of the General Physics
    Section 1. On the nature of the body and its parts.
    Question 1.
    What might the nature of a body or what specifically might the essence of a physical body be?
    Question 2.
    How many and what might the principles of natural bodies be?
    Section 2. On the impenetrability, divisibility, porosity and form of bodies.
    Whether impenetrability is a common property of all bodies.
    Whether and into what are sensible bodies divisible?
    Question 3.
    Whether form and porosity are common to all bodies?
    Section 3. On the rare and the dense; whereas also the vacuum.
    Of what does the rarefaction and condensation of bodies consist?
    Whether there is destruction? Is a vacuum possible?
    Section 4. On the lightness (and/or) heaviness of bodies and the cause of both.
    What and of what sort is the cause of lightness
    What is, and in what, does the heaviness of bodies consist
    Section 5. On local motion in particular; its cause, impediments and laws.
    What is and how many kinds of local motion are there; wheresoever is rest?
    What is the specific cause of local motion
    How many impediments of motion are there, where andetr? in bodies, positive force of inertia
    Section 6. On motions in kind
    Whether heavy things accelerate their motion whereby, a certain proportion of the motion having been determined, the acceleration procedes.
    What is the cause of a motion at one time refracted at another time reflected and the laws of both.
    What is the striking or collision of bodies and what are the laws of bodies at times elastic and at other times lacking springiness.
    Question 4.
    What would be the principal of general composite motion.
    Section 7. On the equilibrium and position of bodies.
    What is the center of gravity and how is it found?
    What is is the general static principle and what is the physical reason of equilibrium?
    Section 8. On the equilibrium of liquids at times among themselves at other times with solids immersed in the same.
    Whether every liquid settles itself at equilibrium and when?
    By what reason does the liquid of vessels in which they are contained reach bottom.
    What about the equilibrium of solids with liquids and their observed immersion.
    Section 9. On heat and cold.
    Of what specifically does heat consist
    Of what specifically does cold consist
    Section 10. On solidity and fluidity.
    One sole question.
    By what is the solidity and fluidity of bodies understood
    Section 11. On taste and smell.
    Of what specifically does taste consist
    Of what specifically does physical smell consist
    Section 12. On sounds.
    Of what specifically does sound consist and how is it propagated
    Last section. On light and colors.
    What is light.
    How to explain the transparency and reflexivity of light.
    Last question.
    What is there about colors to be perceived?
    Zavaleta, Diego Estanislao, -1843
  - Undiano y Gastelú. Ytinerario..., 1799 (Bound)
- Oversize
  - n.d. folio (Ovflat 13)
  - ? Plano de las Yslas Maluinas., 1770 (Ovflat 13)
  - González, José Antonio. Frontera del Sur de la Ciudad de Cordova., 1786 (Ovflat 13)
  - Aleón y la Calle, Juan José. Plano topográfico del punto de Yavi y Posicion de la Vanguardi del Exercito Real., 1812, Mar. 25 (Ovflat 13)